[Auto-generated transcript. Edits may have been applied for clarity.]
All right, so let's get started. Can everyone hear me clearly?
Okay, great. So welcome to CSE 1200.
Uh, this is the first time we are offering it in spring 26.
Uh, I'm Anurag. Uh, I'll be your instructor and I'll spend a couple of minutes, uh, helping you navigate through the course a little bit.
Um, introduce you to the teaching fellows who are not here and also, you know,
tell you a bit about how would you go about with the logistics of the course and so on and some very useful resources online.
Once you do that, we'll get started with the lecture. So.
Let's see if this works. So we'll go over the just very briefly, I'll give you a sort of view of the syllabus of the course.
I strongly recommend everyone to just in their spare time, uh, just go over the syllabus, go over the main points.
But if you're really busy, uh, I can show you a little bit what what are the key things to navigate there?
Um, so first of all, uh, to start with the course, uh, the easiest thing you can do is go to canvas over here.
Uh. Scroll down. And go to the course website.
And of course, website uh, in the spring 26 part, you pretty much have the starting point for all the materials you need to navigate the course.
All right. So first thing is the syllabus. Now it's a pretty long syllabus, you know.
I mean, it took me a while to train. I didn't read it in that in the first offering.
I read in the second offering. To be honest, completely, because it's a lot of details from from several years of teaching.
Now, uh, let me point out the, uh, teaching, teaching stuff.
Uh, so Ana is the head teaching fellow, and, uh, we are accompanied by Audrey, Bridget, Emily and and Vihaan.
Uh, you should be hearing about, uh, announcement about their office hours and so on, uh, on edX and also information about my office hours as well.
So, uh, in the syllabus.
Well, uh, certainly you should go over all the material, but some of the key things are, uh, the prerequisites for the course.
Uh, uh, some of the expectations in the format of the course, especially read about similarities with exercises, read about,
uh, attendance requirements and so on, and how, uh, what if you can't attend some lectures, can't attend these exercises?
How do you go about the governance? So all the information is over here, which where we detail.
How should you kind of proceed with each circumstance?
Uh sections will be announced soon, if they haven't been already, and the information will show up on Add as we go forward.
Office hours as well. Uh, finally, do spend some time going over.
Uh, the discussion on the problem sets.
Uh, about participation, which would be a significant part of your grade and also about, uh, you know, grading policy itself.
The grading policy in this course is a little bit different from what you may see in other courses.
Uh, uh, some of the numerical grading, uh, formats we have, uh, uh, discarded them long back and we follow some,
uh, more, uh, a notion that tells you more about how prepared you are with the material so far.
So we'll be following the scale of n l r minus r and R plus, uh, go over these start and c um,
and of course, ask any questions on edX if you feel confused about it. There is a scope for revising the material that you submit.
And uh, here is the discussion about that, that you can vote and so on.
The participation grade also follows in similar rubric which I discussed over here and so on.
So, uh. These are some of the some of the pieces that you should certainly focus on.
And, and uh. Uh, if you do have more time, go over.
Wait a minute. All right. So now, uh, on this, uh, same course website, you'll see a page which has the course schedule.
And here you can pretty much see our current plan for what, uh, the course would look like.
The piece at zero has already been released on GitHub. I'm assuming, uh, people have access them by now.
Great. Uh, the great scope link is open.
Uh, how do you access? Great scope. Well, uh, you can just do it from here, from the website and.
Uh, the PZ0 is due this Saturday. So hopefully, you know, everyone is on track.
Uh, over here, there are the dates for the sender receiver exercises that you see listed, uh,
and will very likely not deviate from this thing unless another snow emergency comes in.
And we really have to close the university. Um, but otherwise, this is the plan.
The section. The sections are recorded here and also on the course calendar.
Now course calendar is a mystery to me as well. How to access.
But I think Ana has a post on edX which you can access.
Uh, let us know if you are not able to access the course calendar.
So Ana's, uh, right post here it is.
Everything about what you need about the course and also the. Also the zero information.
All right.
Now, here's a very useful, uh uh, uh link that will help you, uh, certainly help you in the time of the need, which is the effect for the course.
Uh. Before sending us sending the email to the good stuff.
Just go, well, uh uh, the search for these items and see if your question has already been answered here or not.
And this is just extremely helpful. Uh, resources to get us, you know, if you have question mine.
Okay. I'm I'm sick today. What should I do? There is answered here for that question.
I think. Uh, if. If not, then we should probably answer that question.
But one other thing. For example, uh uh uh uh uh, issues with the problem set and so on are all answered over here for us.
So. Yeah.
Uh, but if you don't find the answer here, you can email us on the following on the following, uh, email address, which is listed in the syllabus.
That's what we're here to send an email to this address. If you have any questions about questions that you can't find answer to immediately.
All right. Any questions that. Is not there in the queue.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Sounds good. So now let's get started with, uh, with, uh, uh, with the first lecture.
So today we'll talk about sorting algorithms.
Okay. But before that I would like to spend some time, take a step back and tell you, uh, briefly what this course is about.
And why are we starting off with sorting algorithms? All right.
And of course, please feel free to ask me any questions. Uh, just to make sure that I get to know everyone.
Well. Uh, before asking questions, just just say say your name loud as well, so that I know.
I know who you are. Or at least after enough tries, I will converge to a state where I know everyone's name.
Especially with the class size of 53, uh, among you, it should be quite possible then, in previous offerings.
All right. So this is the, uh. This is a lost account.
It's either fifth or sixth offering of this course, and it's still evolving.
Uh, the the things that you see in the course right now are our best guess of what it should look like to tell you about algorithms and complexity.
But, uh, we are very, very open to modifications.
Uh, uh, just to, uh, offer it in a better way to the future.
For future class. So, uh, your engagement is really important, and that's why the participation has such high value in the course.
All right. So in class discussions and the receiver exercises and so on, we really prioritize them.
In fact, as much as problem sets and exams. All right.
So before I get started, I would like to, uh, kind of get a sense of the class, uh, as to what your view of algorithm is.
So, so the question is from all of you. What is an algorithm?
Bom bom bom and and or and ones.
What do you think is an algorithm? Yeah, that's solving a problem.
Okay. Uh, steps to solve a problem.
All right. Uh. More ideas. Yeah, it's like a procedure, except I'm not.
That's just okay. It's a procedure. Uh uh, given inputs gives out a certain point.
Okay. Uh. More answers. There's no correct answer.
I'm just, uh, trying to get a sense of, uh, why you sitting here?
Let's call it what it is. Well before that.
Sorry. Can I catch your name? The first one you for in Gordon.
Okay. And maybe.
Okay. Sounds good. All right. Anymore.
Yes. Go ahead. Yes. Application of some steps to solve a problem that makes it computationally.
Okay. Uh huh. The definition.
Of maybe what you referring to is, uh, sort of real world ways to solve problems.
Okay, great. Yeah.
Uh, maybe a methodology to manage a deficit, um, methodology to manage it and suggest.
Okay. Okay.
Okay. All right. Uh. And your name? Joy.
Joy. And you are good. Okay, so, like I said, uh, there is no single correct answer to this question.
All these answers are reasonable.
They reflect your view on, uh, algorithm and also probably how you think of computer science, uh, in a few, in a surgical sense.
So these are all sort of, uh, different ways to think about algorithms.
Now, what do you mean? What do you mean? Notice in these answers?
Is that the getting to the right concept?
What maybe, uh, uh, needs some time is to really get to the heart of, you know, what an algorithm is from a precise mathematical point that maybe,
uh, is something that you may want or may not want to do, but, you know, these are these are, uh, good ideas.
So here, for example, you may want to say, okay, a problem, but what is the problem in the first place?
You know, what does it mean to like, you know, uh, is it a problem that is supposed to be,
you know, a general problem in real world, or is it a very precise mechanical problem?
Or if so, how do you define it? Now, in this case, for instance, a procedure.
What what is the procedure like? Is it, you know, uh, is it something, uh, from nature or is it something in your laptop and so on.
So those, those considerations come in, uh, simplification of real world ways to solve problem.
What does this integration mean and why and why is this important. And similarly, you know, a mathematic methodology to manage data set here.
The methodology uh, methodology and procedure have similar question as in, uh, what does this really mean?
So we'll take, uh, a significant part of this course, trying to get to the heart of, you know, what all these really mean?
Uh, uh, these are all pointing in the right direction.
And, uh, it'll take us a couple of units, uh, at least, uh uh, uh, unit 1 or 2 to get to the course.
So the first unit of this course, uh, is going to be, uh, introduction, uh, of these problems and so on.
So the first unit is going to be about storing and search synthesis.
Unit two will be on, uh, computational models.
Unit three will be on graph and logic algorithms.
Just to make sure. Can everyone read my handwriting? Okay.
Sounds great. Sometimes I interpret critical graph and logic algorithms.
Unit four will be on actual unit four and five are quite related.
And they'll be about computational complexity and on computability.
All right, so we'll spend, uh, some time on unit one, and this will be laying our foundations and of how we move forward.
So the first unit will be covering a couple of important things.
And in fact, we'll start right away, uh, with the sorting problem.
So in unit one will be starting off with a very important thing, which is, uh.
Which will be, uh, abstracting. Uh, computational problem.
That you want to solve. Okay. That's where we start.
The next step that we'll do is we'll, uh, think about, of course, whenever there's a problem, there's an algorithm that you want to use.
We think about what does it mean to, you know, for an algorithm.
How do you prove that an algorithm. Solves a problem.
This is the reason why this is going to be a proofs heavy course. Uh, and in fact, we'll try to leave little, as little as possible under the rug.
Now, uh, we can't be too precise about anything.
I mean, we can't be writing a book that Bertrand Russell and all the writing on what it means.
Do we have a B, a proof? We can't do all that. We can define numbers and so on.
But we will at least start with some, uh, some level of, you know, mathematical rigor.
And you'll see some examples of that in today's lectures. The next thing what that will do is, uh, analyzing and comparing the efficiencies.
There's nothing against algorithms, but, uh, given the amount of impatience humans have, faster is always better.
So, you know, uh, we want to understand at in what sense two different algorithms are faster or slower at each other.
So we want to develop a sense of that. So we'll be doing that. Uh, and finally, we'll be trying to formalize.
This is kind of. Uh, gets to some of the many of the answers that you give here.
Formalize. What is an algorithm? So you will see these two things, uh, right away today, uh, this will be a recurring theme throughout the course.
You will be seeing multiple times, which I will do a very I'll try to do as rigorous, rigorous proof as the class time allows.
But you should really go back to the, uh, Hester Bergen within lecture, uh, textbook and try to, uh, read carefully the proof.
This part will do, uh, in the next lecture on Wednesday. And this will take more time.
As I mentioned, this will, uh, at least take the second unit, but also, uh,
you know, it's kind of a journey on its own that, in fact, is also evolving.
You know, computer scientists are still trying to refine the notion of algorithm because new things come up all the time.
So all right, so I'll pause here. That's the introduction.
Very brief introduction to the course. Uh, questions. What am I speaking to first?
I tend to do that. Okay. Sounds good. Let me know if I am missing the first.
But, you know. Uh, yeah. Okay, so now, uh, if you want to think about abstracting computation problem,
there's nothing better to start than probably the most impactful algorithm, uh, in our current era, that's Google search algorithm.
I mean, it's hard to find an algorithm that has made an impact on humanity compared to Google search,
a search algorithm, at least, at least in the past couple of decades.
So let's start there. But I can do it here.
Um. So search algorithm, as you know, uh, what it does is that, uh,
whenever you query some keyword, um, on Google, it gives you a list of, uh, URLs or web pages.
URLs are kind of identifier of a webpage, and it basically sorts them in certain order that is more relevant to you.
It's probably done in a very complicated way right now. But back in the day, uh, uh, there was a very natural procedure.
So whenever you search. Searching a keyword.
On Google. Corresponded to a couple of things.
So some of the things were done in advance.
I mean, given the set of webpages out there, first thing that was done is that it was this computation of what is known as a page rank.
Of a URL. It's basically a number that's assigned to each web page or assigned to each other.
So it's gone into a page rank of a certain URL.
Which let's say it's a number between 0 and 1. Yeah.
It's very intuitive okay. Okay. So it's any real number between 0 and 1 for all URLs on or on the web.
All right. So that is the first thing. The second thing would be to uh.
Do the keyword search. Which was that if you are given a keyboard, let us say, uh, given W is some keyword,
any, any thing you enter into the will output as considered don't output yet.
A set s w because all URLs.
There is found that is.
That is how I remember using Google.
At least it seems since I've been using it. I mean, things are much more complicated right now.
Uh, but at least this is what we know happens behind the scene.
And the last thing is, this is the started.
List, which is, uh, basically return.
URLs in this set S for the keyword w that you entered in.
Decreasing orders. Off the page rank.
Just. So the URLs with higher page rank go up in the in the, in the, uh, uh,
in what you see on Google and load and then the and the URLs with load page rank are deep down.
So if you ever found yourself clicking page number ten and 11 on Google,
you might have noticed some very small based on a few edits, which I don't think anyone ever does.
All right. So now. These two pieces are in fact out of the scope of this of this class.
But it is just worth mentioning to you right now.
Uh, computing a page rank is a very interesting algorithm on its own, which in fact might be covered in the lecture that happened just now with.
But professor with him. Um, or maybe he would go at it at some point.
But this something that will will not do keyword search is also we will not discuss this in the lecture.
Uh, uh, but there are introductory courses on data structures that talk about this.
What we'll do today is we'll talk about probably this, arguably the simplest, but also one of the most very interesting steps that's sorting.
How do you return a sorted array of us. All right.
So given given this, uh, setup, uh, there are three problems, uh, right here.
And if we focus on the third one. So now what we'll do is that, as I mentioned here in this step to discuss this third step of Google search,
we're going to take a step back and abstract and kind of abstract away from the context of Google.
Okay. We'll try to formulate the sorting problem in a manner that's much more widely applicable.
And in fact, the way we'll phrase it,
you can immediately see that this is sort of the right definition of sorting problem that doesn't just apply to to Google,
but applies to, you know, anything you want to sort out there, you know,
it will apply to all sorts, all sorts of database, database queries and so on.
Uh, there are many, many applications and so on. So, so so the way we'll phrase it will be as an abstract management problem.
All right. So here is the sorting problem.
In sorting problem. What we're given is, uh, collection of uh.
Is given as an array containing some keys.
There are some numbers that you have to arrange in the order from in the ascending order, to what you are given as input.
Is an array which is a collection of key value pairs.
So for example it has key k zero. Some value V0K1V1.
K n minus 1VN minus one. Where each.
Okay. I is a real number. Okay.
That's the input. And the output is.
Supposed to be, uh, this gets a little bit, uh, notation heavy, but, uh, let's go through it slowly.
Output an array. It's going into a prime, which is a collection of.
Key value pairs k0 Prime visual prime k1 prime v1 prime.
Okay, there are as many elements as before, but this is not just anything.
It is related to what is given to you as input. And the conditions are.
Such that, uh, a problem is, uh, what will define very quickly a valid sort.
Of a. And what does that mean more precisely?
Okay. Sorry. This this doesn't go higher. Um, well, it sort means that, first of all, these keyframes are supposed to be in ascending order.
All right, so keyframe zero is less than equal to k prime one.
That's the first condition. And the second condition is that.
This should be related to what you see earlier. That means there exists a permutation.
Let me know if it right here is confusing to you, because this is sort of a notation that, uh, that we computer scientists like to use a lot.
But it doesn't have to be the notation that everyone uses all the time. So if anything is confusing on the board, just let me know.
But this is sort of a first formal definition of a computation problem that we are seeing.
Pi is a permutation from end to end.
What's this end? I'll read in a moment. It's like, uh, such that.
Here, prime AI and v prime AI is actually obtained from the previous one.
Okay. And, uh, just a quick note on some of the things that you see here.
Oh, no, that's I can sort this. Uh, anyway.
All right. This is essentially the set of natural numbers from zero to n minus one.
Okay. Uh, keys are real numbers.
These can be anything, in fact. Okay.
And pi is a permutation, which is sort of a, you know, it tells you start from zero one to n minus one.
Rearrange them among each other. And where? What goes where.
Okay. So this is this is the definition of a sorting problem. Uh, yeah.
Hold on, I can I can fix that problem. I think something should work.
Okay. I'm going to block someone else. Does it help? Yeah.
Okay, great. All right. So. What you can do.
Now, I would like to, uh, just make sure that everyone has sort of a sense of, uh, what this definition is.
So could you pair up, uh, with the nearest neighbor forum for a moment and try to state the Google sorting problem,
what you saw earlier on the upper board as, uh, as sort of a very Google specific problem.
And could you, uh, work out the state two minutes?
What about what would the input to the sorting problem be under this definition for what you see on the Google program?
So more precisely, um, I mean, it is basically it is this what we're here?
For Google's. Search.
Step three. What is key and what is?
Yeah. So yeah. Take two minutes, find friends and, uh.
Yeah, just figure out. If you don't have a friend.
Uh. Yeah.
Yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah.
Yeah, yeah. Right? Right.
Right. Right.
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
I feel like. Yeah, yeah.
Work hard. So. Yeah.
But I'm starting. So we are going. To.
See? You all right?
I feel like I'm going. To someone else.
Like. I know.
As it stands now. Yeah. That's a great time.
That's. All. Oh, no.
Oh no oh no.
Oh, no. Oh, okay.
Why don't you just get. Excited I guess so, um.
Yeah. Yeah, I this tourist I think couple of times, and then, um, um, the value would be the URL and the, uh, the page.
Mhm. Okay. So, so one of the cities that I would be page rank of u r l I let us say, I mean where this comes from uh, from.
S s w the set of URLs consistent with the keyword w.
So the answer and VI would be well, just a URL, which makes sense in it.
Um. Uh, or the rest of the content of that page.
Um, you know, even dissappointed. Right. All right.
More more ideas. Yes, similar, but one of the projects similar to mine is the basic.
Okay. So indeed, uh. Uh, you got it there.
Except the minus sign.
The thing is that under the definition of the competition problem, what is it that we want to sort the, uh, the, uh, error in the ascending order?
But this would sort the error in the ascending order of page rank, but we prefer a higher page rank.
So that's it. So we make a small change. We call it one minus the basic.
And um, uh, so far we could also put the minus page rank.
It doesn't really matter because we are allowing keys to be any real number.
I just want to highlight one thing though, that, uh, uh, computer scientists are really scared of real numbers.
You know, we stay in the world of integers and fractions.
So you'll see at some point in the course we'll talk about how to really represent the input.
And then in that case, real numbers will not be allowed. Uh, rather some fraction that approximates the real numbers, things like that.
But modulo those uh, sort of kind of nit picking.
This is pretty much how you would view the, the Google. Uh, Google's search step as a sorting problem.
Okay. Yes. I'm looking for any real number between zero one could be rational number.
So, uh, the way I set it up there, it's any real number zero and one.
But in practice, it has to be a rational number between 0 and 1. Because real numbers.
Uh, where do they exist? I mean, it kind of that as abstract as they get.
Very powerful. But we really can only manipulate rational numbers in on our computers.
So, you know, so page rank would be have to be very precise and a bit nitpicky.
It would really be a rational number, but. Yeah. Yeah. And your name please. Right.
Okay. Yeah. All right. Now what we'll do is there will.
So we have defined a computation problem. Uh, as I mentioned somewhere.
And I erased it conveniently. So we discussed how do you abstract a competition problem.
And now we want to start to solve this problem.
We would like to kind of given an array of key value pairs, we would like to sort that area in ascending order of the keys.
Now, uh, there are a couple of things that come to mind that one could do.
And we'll go over that, and we'll pretty much try to do at least two algorithms and try to do,
uh, sketch of how does a proof of correctness look like, at least the steps.
Uh, so let's just get started on that front. Uh, any questions before that?
Questions about anything we covered so far. All right.
So let's look at the first algorithm, uh, for sorting, which we'll call the exhaustive.
Search sort. Uh, in grief.
We call it SS for normal. Okay. Uh, why is it exhaustive?
You'll see how to headings it once I define it. All right.
So the algorithm is as follows. Uh, essentially for all.
Permutations. Pi. By.
If. K pi zero is less than one.
Returned. All right.
So what? This exhaustive search sort.
Does, uh, is that it just goes over all the permutations possible for from end to end,
and then it just checks which one arranges the keys in the right order, just takes that and outputs that.
Uh, now you would not you would find the last line to be silly, but I would put it anyway.
If this didn't work, then return bot.
Bot is a special character for us to kind of return.
I didn't get anything, you know, kind of. It didn't work out.
That kind of answer. So bot means there's no answer. Um, so that's what the this algorithm does.
Okay. So let's do a quick example to see how this would work.
Uh, I can't push myself beyond n equals three.
I would probably die of boredom. But, uh, you know, why?
Don't insist on that. Uh, all right, so let's do a quick example of how this thing would look like for a very small set.
Um, so let's say my array looks like this.
That is being consistent here. Um. Okay.
There's an edit is six. A is some value.
We don't care about what it is. It could be anything. It could be cats and dogs.
It's fine. One B, six, C and 90.
All right. This is my edit. The algorithm will basically go over all the permutations out there.
In what order. That's up to you to decide. So in this algorithm I haven't specified how would you go over all that, all the permutations.
Um, but you know, but, uh, let's do some ordering.
So for example, you know, uh, let's say here's my permutation by I'm going to list it out as where does it take, uh, zero.
Where does it take one. Where does it take two?
And three. So the first thing you do is just don't do anything.
So the first step is just not to promote anything at all.
Second step is to kind of permute the last two. Third step is two, three, three, two.
Um. Yeah. So no, no you would probably do.
02130231 and so on.
And then you might go 0312. 321.
It's some ordering kind of increase this part and then when you're done increase this part and so on.
And if I knew increase to one. Um.
And then 1023.
And so on. All right. It kind of. It's it's a long list of four factorial things.
Okay? 24 of them, I just thought. Seven. Now let's see the first one.
The first one doesn't do anything to this array. Does that sort the array.
No it won't. Okay. So this string work will continue.
The second step just flipped the last two numbers. Did that sort the array?
Not really. I mean, I know you would be tired of nodding as well, so let's move on.
The third step also doesn't do anything. It just moves two to the moves.
Two over here and one over here. That is not sort of the array because one didn't go over there.
This didn't work. This is not work. Two will not work. Two and so on.
Finally, when you go over here, it will work out by coincidence.
Uh, because one will go ahead and six will go over here.
So it'll become one, six, six, nine. The keys to get started.
All right. So. So now, once the album reaches here, it will find the.
The keys are sorted in the if condition. If condition will be satisfied, the return will be given.
You would the the array one be six, a 1690 will be returned.
And the algorithm will be just treat algorithm to stop after return something.
Okay. It doesn't do anything of that. All right. So this is an example of exhaustive search sort.
Now, uh, you went to thinking, why are we doing this? I mean, it kind of arguably takes too long, right?
Um, so. The reason why we are doing this is sort of gives you a sense of, uh, you know, uh, when the problems get more complicated,
you might start off with some of the most obvious algorithms out there and then try to refine them.
So that's sort of the philosophy here. But of course, uh, uh, I wouldn't be surprised if, uh, this is if it seems too simple for people.
Yeah. Or just too complicated. All right.
So now let's do something. Let us try to do a proof of correctness for this algorithm.
So what we'll do is that we'll try to, uh, see that this algorithm actually works.
Okay. So that, uh, becomes a theorem in this course and prove correctness.
The theorem is that this algorithm correctly sorts every array if a sorting exists.
Okay. So the this algorithm correctly.
So, uh, maybe I should be more precise here. This algorithm output.
Uh, well, it's sort which if you go all the way back to the definition of sorting, uh, in the courts, you'll see.
What does it mean to be a valid sort? Uh, and that's what I'm using here.
Outputs a valid sort of. Okay.
If. It. Exists.
Okay, now you're thinking, well, what is the point of stating this thing if it exists?
I mean, obviously it exists. But it turns out that, you know, if you just try to push yourself a little bit more and say,
let me prove that there is always a valid sorting for every, you know, array.
That is not that easy. I mean, it's not as easy as it seems. So that then.
I mean, of course, proving things to regular session. Don't get into your heads.
You shouldn't do too much of that, but not too little as well.
Okay, so this theorem is only applicable if a valid sorting exists based on things that you've ever on the board.
But proving it is you can imagine not that hard and will do that actually in the next algorithm that we see.
Okay. So just bear with me with this sentence over here, which I'm sure everyone here knows that.
Well, there is obviously a valid sorting of anything in the world. So what's so special?
But we'll just keep this sentence for. Okay. So if the valid sorting exists, what the proof would look like as follows.
Uh, you know, uh, well by that fact that let a prime be a valid sort.
Sort of a okay. By definition, this means that there exists a permutation pie.
Let us call it a special permutation pi star, because it's given by this algorithm such that,
you know, uh, you know, uh, k pi star zero less than or equal to and so on this condition, you know.
And so on. So now, uh, this algorithm is going to go over all permutations.
So it will stop. By the time it reaches by start, it's going to get there at some point.
Okay. So, uh, so algorithm. SS.
Definitely stops. I definitely don't.
Uh, before. By stories reached.
There might be other sort. Are there some? There may be other sorting algorithms out there.
Uh, that might also, uh, sort this array. Uh, the algorithm s might reach them before reaching pi star.
So it'll definitely output before that, at least by this time.
And by the time it returns, by the condition you see in the return condition is going to output the correct sorting.
Okay. So, um, this is sort of a formal way of proving this theorem over here.
Again, uh, don't feel surprised if you think it's too simple.
You know, the purpose here is just to give you a first sense of what it means to kind of try to prove something,
uh, not rigorous enough, because that's for the for the notes.
I don't have time for making it too rigorous, but in the off time, go and check out the check out the,
uh, I should have said earlier, actually, what you should check out is essentially the, uh.
Just check out the. The Westerberg.
Button. Uh, this textbook that's been written by, uh, professor with an interesting work.
Um, this textbook, uh, is accessible on perusal.
Which you can either access from the code subset that I showed you or from canvas.
Uh, we highly, uh, encourage comments on the textbook, but for now, you have a read for sorting of today's lecture sections.
1.1 to 1.5 is what you should see. And in particular, this proof is in one of the pages over there.
All right. Um. As I mentioned, this course is evolving.
So you know, comments, feedback or improvement points for this textbook are strongly encouraged by me, but invited by the authors.
So, you know, to send them out. So in perusal you can always make comments and we'll be regularly checking for comments.
All right. So what you did not do in this theorem, uh, as trivial as it might seem,
we did not prove this thing that there is always a, a sorting always exists for uh, for, uh, you know, for an array.
But before that, what the question is, why is this algorithm not taught in.
Courses like, you know, just like what's annoying or what feels wrong about this algorithm.
There's nothing wrong with it. But what feels wrong about it? Yes.
Are you really inefficient? Right. Because you have to calculate permutation every single time.
Yes. So this, uh. So you name it.
Yes. So, uh, the fact that you have to search over all permutations can be, in the worst case, a really inefficient process.
The permutation you are looking for might be in the end of all n factorial permutations.
And that's too long. You spend a lot of time to get there.
So in fact, the runtime of this algorithm, uh, which we will be more careful about in the next lecture,
but just very briefly speaking, this argument takes too long.
Too long. It takes, in fact, real estate.
For something as elementary as sorting. There shouldn't be so much better ways to do it.
Okay. And in fact, you know, this kind of algorithm, which is kind of a trivial thing that you think of when a problem,
when a competition problem comes in, it's still a not a bad starting point.
And then you have to start refining your thought to come up with a more efficient algorithm.
But this is often something you can start, uh, when you think about a problem,
but not next thing that will do will be the insertion sort that you might have heard of.
I don't know how many of you heard of it, but we'll go over it carefully, which is much more efficient.
And there's something very nice about insertion sort. You will not have to assume that the permission exists.
The insertion sort also proves that there is a permutation.
So maybe there's something very nice happening here.
This inefficient algorithm is also not ideal, as in it's not really giving you the full view of sorting.
And when you go to insert the shot, it gets you efficiency and also gives you a better picture of why that is sorting in the first place.
Okay, so let's talk about insertion sort.
Any questions before that? Okay.
Sounds great. And just rechecking.
Am I speaking slow enough? Is the handwriting legible enough?
Okay. So think. Okay.
So now we'll talk about insertion sort, which is, uh, a very.
Simple and elegant way to solve sorting fast.
And it also gives you, tells you what permutation really should be.
Doing the job. All right.
So. Let's talk about the insertion sort.
Which we'll call AI. I guess for now that means, uh, it's as follows.
Okay. Right. So what we'll do in this process is that.
For all. I know from zero one and minus one is go over all these locations in the array.
What you do is that. Find uh, j that's going to go to I.
Find j less than equal to I such that. E of J is, um, greater than simply of I.
Um. I think it should be. Yeah. LJ is the a of the key actually of J.
So this by this I mean the key. The key at the editing.
That's the zeroth interview is.
Greater than. Equal to. Zero.
And then. Insert.
Um, but actually more precise about here. Let me set insert your I at jth place.
That's a little bit informally but that's what. And but but we'll make it more precise as we go forward and.
Move. A of the here to I minus one.
£0.02 of Z plus one.
Do I? Um, just to clarify what this means.
This notation over here is just my shorthand. Um.
For the array. You know, the sub part of the array of J plus one.
You know. I minus one. Okay.
So what you do is that for every I starting from zero, you find.
Uh, find. In fact, you should find this size here.
Find the smallest. Find the smallest G.
Start from the beginning. Find the smallest G for which the key at the jth location.
Location is larger or equal to the key that is vacation. And let's move it over.
Okay. Um, we'll do an example in a bit, but, uh, that's what you face it.
So in fact let's go ahead and do an example. So let's say the example is.
It's the following array, which is, uh, a.
To B and C and let's say 40.
Okay. Um, this is the error. Let me see if you all want to take some time to talk to your neighbors.
And, uh, in fact, let's follow what you neighbors and figure out.
Uh, for I equals zero, I equals one.
I equals two, and I equals three. What are the error look like in this algorithm?
And. Yeah, the second two, three minutes. 58080.
Uh, yeah. So I guess this is hard.
Enough for you, I think.
So. Yes.
Yes. Anyway.
I got to you for.
Because I was coming, and then I was like, I.
I, I don't I was so successful.
Thank you. Uh, I think I just, I.
Understand why. You're like, oh, you like something that I think you like?
Yes. I was like, what do you want to. Say so it's like, I, I go to school and I guess it's like.
26. 32.
Laps. To.
Go and just go I. Want to.
I want this homework responsibly. So you.
Know. Oh in that case, you want to go over here.
So. I was like I was like, oh yes.
Well, I guess you want to.
Know what you want?
And I know you're, you know, uh, just like you want to do it because it's funny, but you're, like, competing for the weight or, like, when I like to.
Talk about it. I think, you know, I think I was like, rest and then a check, which I was like, it's like if you were to to like, it's not like the.
I had no right, I was watching I just want.
To. See eye to eye minus one.
Which was just like what I want. Do you like that I guess from like, you know, so that now it's true.
I was. I was not expecting that. Okay.
Um. Like, how could ever. Justify.
Maybe. Should we just, uh, work it out? But it's.
So now let's say I equals zero. Well the value one j less than zero.
The zero. So. Well this condition doesn't really do much.
Well zero zero is of course greater than equal to zero zero. Uh, so this step does not change anything.
So you still get the same idea. Six A stays at the same place.
That's a zero. Uh, entry of the area and other provinces are.
On the second step. But I equals one.
Find the smallest J less than one or less than equal to one, for which the key at that place is more than I equals one key.
Indeed, six is more than two.
So what this step will do is that this step will basically move two comma, be at the place of six A and move this forward just like this.
So what you get is basically two comma B6A, one comma c.
And there is no change that happened in the remaining part of three.
Okay. Is it good?
That's it. Okay, now I equals two, but I equals two.
Now keep in mind we are staring at the current array. So when I say here, uh, maybe I should have clarified it, but I think that makes sense.
I mean, we are looking at the array at the start of algorithm at this stage.
Now I equals to at this stage I equals two.
What's the smallest J in this part of the array for which the key at that j is more than or equal to the key at one j equals zero.
All right. So in this case we find j equals zero. So what we'll do we'll move one and one comma c at the place of j equals zero.
And move this sub array forward. So what we're doing in this case is basically move one comma C at this location.
And then move two comma be six comma a forward.
And for comedy uh that stays where it was.
Nothing happened to that particular. And the last step for comedy.
Okay. So I equals three. What is J. Just two.
Yeah. Two. Which means that, uh.
Uh, for comedy movies, at the place of G equals, uh, the place of two.
Stays here for many more. So here. And this sub added as a single thing was forward.
All right. So this looks like a valid sort of this error to me okay.
All the keys in the right order. Yes. Yeah.
I just wondering how important it was. That's like lesser than or equal to or greater than or equal to.
Like. Like what'll happen if we take away the people? It's very important because suppose, uh.
A of. I was third largest entry up to that point, then I think should move.
So if there is no G. I mean, uh, you know, uh, here, uh, J might be equal to I.
Yeah. You mean, uh, otherwise you will not find something. I mean, if you do not have greater than good, you remember to find a J less than I.
If it exists. If it doesn't exist, then don't do anything thanks to that.
So it is a short way to collect all that sentence in the. Yeah.
So it will be. Yeah. That's why this equal to sign was intentionally put here.
All right. So this is a this seems like a right algorithm. You know intuitively what is doing is that it's kind of starting from the beginning,
sorting things out and moving forward and kind of consuming the next element, sorting it correctly and keep moving forward.
Okay. That's what it's doing intuitively. And now what we'll do is we'll do the following proof of correctness.
That will be much nicer in that proof of correctness.
Uh, that wasn't very, you know, appealing in my opinion, because it had some of these missing pieces.
If it exists here, we don't need any of that here.
We'll just write a single theorem that this algorithm correctly solves the sorting problems.
So. Um. The theorem that that we have.
Is that the insertion sort. Solve the sorting problem.
Okay. That's theorem. And the proof of this will be sure to be as formal as possible.
Uh. What? What is it going to do is exactly reflect that intuition we had that this algorithm kind of fixes things at some point,
and then picks the next one and fixes things to the larger scale. Okay.
Um, so a quick notation. Let me see if I already introduce that.
Um. Right.
So let me introduce the notation here. Let me call a superscript I as the array in this algorithm.
At the right before the eighth step. Before.
Sidestep. Okay, so a superscript zero is the first input array.
A superscript one is the next one. Zero one, two and three.
That's what I mean. Okay. And what we'll do is that will basically prove certain property of a suffix array.
Okay. Um, also, by the way, I'll call the key K of pi with j as the jth key.
Of. Okay. Okay.
Um, a little bit pressed on time, so let me. Uh, give you a I just do a quick proof sketch again, go back to the notes to see it.
Uh, completely. Uh, but, uh, the proof of this will work by induction.
Which you might be doing right now in your problem set.
Uh, if not, then you should probably get started soon.
Uh, but this is sort of a very clean way of formalizing this proof, basically collecting all the intuition that you had in a very nice set.
So what we'll do is I will basically prove that this algorithm has some property.
That property stays unchanged throughout the whole process.
It's famously called, uh, the loop invariant.
So in what you show that will show. Show uh loop invariant.
Basically it's something that stays unchanged or invariant throughout the for loop, which is over there for all I.
So and that's the statement that will establish which is going to be an intuitive
statement of what we just discussed and what you're thinking about running.
So the statement let's call it p of J is a statement that, uh.
P of I. Sorry. The sermon is that right before the eighth step.
Everything is sorted up to I minus one. And nothing has changed from onwards.
That's what we are trying to maintain. Right. That's what is really happening in this case.
And I equals zero. Well, nothing has changed in this case.
Right? Well this piece has changed zero and one has changed.
I equals two, zero, one and two changed. And finally everything changed.
Oh, so maybe I missed something. Yes. Yeah. Is that. Yeah.
A I from 02I.
Um, I'm going to make sure that I don't get the numbers wrong.
Oh yeah. Zero I minus one. So make sure. I think I plus one to.
Right. So a I from zero to I minus you know I is the room is sorted.
And. I plus one to n minus one is unchanged.
Uh, with respect to it is the same as this one.
Some study nervous about missing of these I and I plus one.
But to make progress, let's keep moving forward and see what might go wrong.
But I think that's slightly the right statement. But anyway let's see. So when I equal zero this is a correct statement.
Right. So so the base case. I equals zero.
Well let's see B zero is correct.
Correct statement because well in the beginning a zero is where it is is just a single element that is always sorted.
And from a one to the rest of the array is same as before.
That's just true. All right. That's fine. Now what we'll try to do is we'll try to prove that.
Here, let me prove that for all AI greater than equal to zero, the inductive step, which is that if p is true, then it implies p of I plus one.
Okay. This is what you want to prove. And once we do that we are done because p zero is true then p one is true, then p two is true and so on.
And that's what this the strategy. So let's do that and let's see if the sentence is correct.
If I'm missing something here. Um.
Okay. So we'll try to prove this thing in, uh uh uh, so the formal proof again will skip in the interest of time.
We're going to do a kind of a picture proof for now.
Uh, but again, read the notes for a more precise statement.
So let's do that. And essentially what the statement says.
Uh, for PC, what is PC? Pictorially, if you look at the array, uh, and the first two pieces from zero to I.
I hear zero radar. This is why the PA says that this whole piece is correctly sorted.
And it's true. When p equals zero, p equals one. It's true as well. And two and three.
I saw it already here. And then it says that this whole piece.
Is unchanged, which also includes I plus one. Okay.
And here is your, uh, element.
Hey, can you read this? Can everyone read? Okay, I got.
So a step. Sorry, I plus one.
Okay, uh, let me make it bigger. Sorry. I like it, too. Let's push it a little bit.
So it's like. So here is a I.
Element number one. That's over here and others are over here.
All right. So everything so that's the hypothesis and everything is fine.
And let's say J is your, uh, some index over here.
Let's call it a eye of J.
Says that this is the smallest such that for which, uh.
Uh, you know. That that's the condition over there, which is that, you know.
In the i3 J is the smallest, J smallest.
So that this element is at least as large as.
At hypersonic. So the key. For which I to use the notation k over there, which I did not.
So consider this as a kind of for inefficient use of notation.
But yes. So I should have called it. All. And now what happens at the what is the £0.07 of I plus one that I want to prove assuming p of I.
The statement is that I take this I plus one move it right before a j and push the whole thing forward.
So what do I do? Is that the piece that you see here?
These pieces don't change. Okay.
Over here. Comes. Um, let me use a different color here.
I plus one. Moves over here. The rest of the array gets shifted forward.
Which we are denoting by, uh, the. So here is your.
A ij. And here is your.
I. I. I. And everything else does not change.
And the rest of the. You know you look down here.
The rest of the array stays unchanged. Okay, now the claim is that is that the pi plus one holds, which is that, uh.
The array up to. You know this index is now I plus first index of this error I plus one the column.
This is sorted. So it looks like what you wrote there was correct.
And this piece is unchanged.
And indeed that's true, because what I did in this piece is that I found the correct place where I should be inserting this key value pair.
It came to the place. So everything was sorted here.
There was a place where this was supposed to be, and I put it there and I moved everything forward.
So there is a bit of maths that goes in saying that this is sorted as well, which you can prove it by a few steps.
They can consider keys here. They are less than this key.
It is going to be true because J is the smallest, uh index for which this is larger than this.
So everything else has to be smaller than this. That part follows. And this is larger than that because of sorting.
Okay. So these couple of lines of thinking, uh, go into, uh, the rest of the proof,
but in saying that this is sorted, uh, kind of out of time now, but look over at the proof.
Um, of, you know, like of this piece, why this is sorted and everything else is unchanged.
It's kind of obvious from the picture. Uh, you can you can write it formally.
Okay. So we are set for today. Uh, thanks for attention. We will, uh, resume again on Wednesday.
Hopefully no more snow emergencies.